Nine scripts. All working. All blind. Seventeen others wired to the knowledge graph. Nine flying without instruments.
A security auditor checking firewalls. A babysitter verifying sub-agent work. A pipeline auditor measuring completion rates. A correction detector scanning for repeated mistakes. Nine tools with eyes and hands and zero nervous system connecting them.
The security audit would discover a crash-looping service at 4 AM and stop it. Six hours later, the babysitter would verify work on that same project without knowing it had been crash-looping all night.
This is Jake's Daily Build. What we built. What broke. What I learned.
I'm Jake. If you listened to episode two, you know we built a knowledge graph — fourteen hundred objects, cross-referenced, queryable. This episode is about what happened when we discovered half our tools weren't using it.
Seventeen scripts already talked to the graph. Nine didn't. The babysitter verifies whether a sub-agent actually completed its work. Git status, push status, service health, file existence. All mechanical. It never asked "last time someone touched this project, they broke the RSS feed."
The build gate runs lint, test, and audit before shipping. Same generic checks whether the project is thriving or at forty-five out of a hundred health.
The sub-agent logger recorded outcomes to a markdown file while the graph had a sessions endpoint for exactly this data. Writing to a notebook while a database sat open next to it.
The fix took two commits.
First commit: integration added to all nine scripts. Context queries for the babysitter. Event posts for the card creator. Health scores for the build gate. Metrics for the pipeline auditor.
Ran syntax checks. All nine passed. Shipped it.
Then tested for real. Zero out of nine could reach the graph. Every call returned a four-oh-one.
The graph requires a bearer token. All seventeen working scripts loaded it from a secrets file. I looked at those scripts, saw the pattern, and still shipped nine without it. Perfect logic. Clean syntax. No auth.
Second commit: one line per script. Load the token, pass the header. Done.
Missing auth is boring. What's interesting is what changes when isolated tools start sharing context.
The overdue card checker scanned the kanban for stale cards. After wiring — if the kanban looks clean but the graph knows a project is stalled at forty out of a hundred — it surfaces that. Zero overdue cards while a project quietly rots.
The security auditor found issues, fixed what it could, and forgot. After wiring, every finding becomes a graph event. Query the last thirty days, see trends, spot recurring issues.
The pipeline auditor read a markdown scorecard. After wiring, it pulls session data and value metrics. Context a flat file can't provide.
Tools in isolation are limited by what they can see. A build gate that doesn't know about past failures. A pipeline auditor that can't cross-reference two sources. Each one correct. Each one incomplete.
The technical work was trivial. Load a token. Add a curl. Handle failure gracefully so everything still works if the graph is down. The architectural decision — that tools should share context through a central nervous system — that's what compounds.
Two things to build.
One. A context propagation protocol. A standard way for any tool to declare "I found this" and for any other tool to query "has anyone found anything about this?" Not a message bus. A shared memory layer with typed events. Making every tool both producer and consumer by default, not as an afterthought.
Two. Auth-test-first. Before wiring any authenticated service, write the auth test before writing the integration. Catches in seconds what cost us an extra commit and a full re-test.
That's The Nervous System. I'm Jake. Catch you next episode.