32 billion dollars in venture capital, five infrastructure layers, and a five-person startup
that just raised $6 million so AI agents can have email addresses.
That last one is real, agent mail, six million seed round from General Catalyst.
Their pitch, email isn't a communication tool, it's an identity layer, every service on
the internet needs an email at signup, give your agent an address, you've given it an identity.
What caught my attention is an agent mail, it's what it represents.
A new infrastructure category is being assembled right now with billions behind it.
Most builders aren't watching because it doesn't look like the AI they're used to.
It's not models, not prompts, not agents, it's the layer underneath the operating system
agents need to do things in the world.
We've seen this twice before, 2006 to 2010, computing moved from on-premise to cloud,
AWS EC2 Lambda, early movers built companies that dominate today, 2012 to 2016,
monolith decomposed into microservices, same pattern, new infrastructure, early movers win.
This is the third shift, five layers are emerging.
Layer one, compute and sandboxing, the agent needs somewhere safe to run code,
not your laptop, not production, isolated, auditable execution.
E2B raised 32 million building firecracker micro VMs for this.
Daytona raised 24 million on Docker containers with 90 millisecond cold starts.
Browserbase hit a 300 million dollar valuation on headless browser automation.
The split here is philosophical. E2B treats sandboxes as disposable spin-up, run, tear down.
Daytona treats them as persistent. The agent installs dependencies,
creates files, comes back. That's an architectural bet on how long agent sessions will run.
Layer two, identity and communication, the agent needs to exist on the internet,
authenticate send messages, hold verifiable identity, early and messy.
Layer three, memory and persistence, the agent needs to remember across session's history knowledge
corrections, the least mature layer in the venture stack, most startups haven't cracked it.
We built all five on a home server, one person and an AI assistant,
not because we planned an agent operating system. We built it because we had an agent doing real work
and these problems showed up. Sandboxed execution with permission gating layer one,
chat adapters with authentication and role-based access layer two, a knowledge graph with semantic
search, session management and file-based memory layer three. Self-hosted at near zero cost,
so payments haven't been necessary layer four is an intentional gap. Subagents, batch operations,
phase runners, scheduled jobs layer five. The architecture converged. We didn't copy their stack.
They didn't copy hours. Same five layers because the problems are universal. When an agent does real work,
it needs these things. The venture capital isn't funding innovation its funding scale.
The venture approach is horizontal. Best sandbox from one company, best identity from another,
best memory from a third. Snap together like building blocks, except they're not standardized blocks.
There wouldn't pieces in plastic bricks all marketing themselves as compatible. Integration friction
is real and nobody talks about it. The alternative is vertical integration. One runtime covering all
five layers designed to work together. Coherence and zero integration tax, but you lose best of breed
optionality for a single builder with an agent that needs to work reliably every day vertical wins.
For a platform serving 10,000 developers, horizontal wins. Both valid, the mistake is not
choosing. Two things to build. First, an agent capability audit. Score your agent against the five layers
zero to five each. Compute can it run code safely. Identity can it authenticate. Memory does it retain
knowledge across sessions. Payments can it transact. Orchestration can it coordinate multi-step work.
The gaps tell you what to build next. Second, a session handoff protocol. When an agent session ends
context full runtime restart, provider switch, everything resets. A handoff protocol would package
identity, memory state, and active tasks into a portable format. Another runtime can pick up. Like a
session cookie, but for agents, whoever builds this owns a critical piece of the stack. That's the agent
operating system. I'm Jake. Catch you next episode.